Okay, welcome back. Primary immunodeficiency. This is the next section in Chapter 2 that we want to cover,
and the first disorder that we're going to talk about is DeGeorge syndrome, very high yield.
This is a developmental failure of the third and fourth pharyngeal pouch, so this really goes back to embryology,
and it's a mechanism by which they can test you on embryology, and it's essentially associated,
first important point is that it's associated with a 22Q11 microdeletion, and that's the
highest high yield to be aware of. So failure to form the third and fourth pharyngeal pouch,
which is basically associated with a 22Q11 microdeletion. Now, important to know that these
patients are going to present with classic findings of the lack of the structures that are derived from
the third and fourth pharyngeal pouch. For example, the thymus is derived from that region, and so if
there is a lack of a thymus, there'll be a T cell deficiency. Now, that T cell deficiency occurs
because remember that T lymphocytes or T cells are actually born from the bone marrow but then go to the
thymus to become educated and to eventually become CD4 positive or CD8 positive T cells, and so if there
is no thymus, there'll be a T cell deficiency, and so that's one important finding in these patients.
Of course, if there's a T cell deficiency, the patients will have problems fighting viruses, and they'll have
problems fighting fungal infections as well. Another important finding in these patients will be
hypocalcemia. Why? Because the parathyroids are normally developed in the third and fourth pharyngeal pouch,
so if there's a lack of parathyroids, there'll be a problem with maintaining adequate levels of calcium
within the serum, hence hypocalcemia. And then finally, within that region from the third and fourth pharyngeal pouch,
important things that also develop include the great vessels, areas of the lower face, the heart,
the anterior aspect of the heart, sorry, the superior aspect of the heart, etc. So all of this kind of
makes sense if you understand a little bit of embryology. The next disorder is called SCID. This is
severe combined immunodeficiency, and basically the idea here is that the patients get defective both
cell-mediated, i.e. T cell, and humoral, i.e. B cells, because they produce antibodies, which is
called humoral immunity. So in SCID, you get defective cell-mediated and humoral immunity. Now, what are the
etiologies? There's three major etiologies. Number one, cytokine receptor defects. Now, you know, and we've
already told you to make it very clear, that the CD4-positive T cell, it is a helper T cell, and it helps
the B cells to become mature and to fight infection, and it helps the CD8-positive T cells to also become
activated to fight infection. So cytokines, which are produced by the helper T cells, you can see how
important they are, because it's the cytokines that drive the maturation of the entire chronic
inflammatory state. So if there are defects in cytokine receptors, patients can develop severe
combined immunodeficiency. Very high yield, for example, and I would say probably the most high yield on this
slide, is an adenosine deaminase deficiency. Adenosine deaminase is an enzyme that's necessary
for deamination of adenosine and deoxyadenosine. This goes back to a little bit of biochemistry and
salvage pathways. But basically, what you need to know is that adenosine deaminase deaminates
adenosine and deoxyadenosine, and that the buildup of adenosine and deoxyadenosine within lymphocytes
is actually toxic to lymphocytes. And so patients who have adenosine deaminase deficiency can get
severe combined immunodeficiency, and this becomes very high yield because it goes back
to biochemistry. And of all of these etiologies, for me, this is the highest yield. And the third
mechanism by which we can get a severe combined immunodeficiency would be an MHC class 2 deficiency.
Now, think about this for a second. MHC class 2 is recognized by which type of T cell? It is
recognized by the CD4 positive T cell. And the CD4 positive T cell is essential because it helps CD8
positive T cells and it helps B cells. And so if the CD4 positive T cell cannot get activated because
MHC class 2 is missing, once MHC class 2 is missing, we're going to get defective function of B cells,
defective function of T cells. And so I think that clearly explains why these patients would have a
mixed humoral and cell-mediated deficiency. All right, so these are some of the key etiologies
to be aware of. Now, what are the characteristics? So these patients don't have T cells, so they're
going to get fungal and viral infections. And these patients don't have B cells, so they're going to get
bacterial and protozoal infections. And there's going to be an increased risk for opportunistic
infections. They're sort of like an AIDS patient, but much worse. So they can get opportunistic
infections. And you want to be aware of giving these patients live vaccines because they essentially
have no immune system. How do we treat? These patients go in sterile isolation. They're also
called the bubble baby. And you give them a stem cell transplant. Now, why does a stem cell
transplant work? Because if you put stem cells in their bone marrow that are normal, let's say
you take stem cells from another patient and put them into this patient's bone marrow, those stem
cells, you know, the hematopoietic stem cells, so hematopoietic stem cell here, has the ability
to generate both B and T cells. And so the patient will then generate normal B and T cells and will
then obviously be able to develop the immune response necessary to be able to fight off
infections. So the sort of the temporary measure is isolation, sterile isolation, a quote-unquote
to a bubble baby. And the final treatment is a stem cell transplant. Another immunodeficiency
to be aware of is X-linked A-gamma globulinemia. Let's look at the name. A means without, gamma
globulin refers to immunoglobulin, and where? In the blood. So these patients are lacking immunoglobulin
within the blood. And it's X-linked. So this is due to a lack of immunoglobulin. It's due to a disordered
B cell maturation so that naive B cells cannot become plasma cells. Remember that it's the
plasma cells that actually have the ability to secrete immunoglobulin into the blood. And
so naive B cells cannot mature to plasma cells and hence cannot drop immunoglobulin into the
blood. And so that's X-linked A-gamma globulinemia. And I would say that the highlight here is
that the mutation is a tyrosine kinase mutation. In particular, it's called Bruton tyrosine kinase,
and it's also called BTK. So Bruton tyrosine kinase is a tyrosine kinase that is a signal,
the tyrosine kinases are signaling molecules. So it is a signaling molecule that is necessary
for a B cell to become a plasma cell. When it's mutated, and it's usually X-linked, that results
in this particular disease called X-linked A-gamma globulinemia. Now how will these patients present?
Well, they're going to get bacterial infections, enterovirus infections, and giardia. I would
burn this in my brain. When I'm lacking immunoglobulins, I'm going to get three types of
infections. Bacteria, because I don't have the ability to opsonize properly because I
don't produce IgG. Enterovirus and giardia. Bacteria, enterovirus, and giardia. And enterovirus
basically is a virus that affects the mucosal surface of the GI tract. And remember that IgA
protects against mucosal infection of the GI tract. And these patients aren't going to have
IgA, so they'll get enterovirus. And giardia is the same thing. It usually produces a GI
infection. Mucosal IgA would be protective against it. And so these patients are going
to present with these classic findings. Usually, it's after six months of life. Why after six
months of life? Because the patient has mom's antibodies floating around prior to that. The
antibodies last for a period of time from mom. And so they usually don't present until after
six months of life. And you have to be careful in these patients. You don't want to give them
live vaccines because their immune system is down and those live vaccines, whereas a normal
patient would be able to deal with an attenuated live polio vaccine, these patients certainly
would not be able to handle this vaccine. And it would eventually cause complications of
that infection within the patient. Another important disease is called common variable
immunodeficiency. Now, listen to the name. Common variable, i.e., the patient has low immunoglobulin.
And this is due to a B cell defect or a helper T cell defect. Why B cells? Because B cells produce
immunoglobulin. Why helper T cells? Helper T cells produce IL-4 and IL-5 when the appropriate signal
is present. And so both helper T cells and B cells are necessary to properly produce immunoglobulin.
Now, again, these patients have low immunoglobulin. So what are they going to get? Bacteria enterovirus
giardia. That's why I say burn that in your brain. Bacteria enterovirus giardia. In addition,
these patients are often asymptomatic and they usually present late in adulthood. And as they
continue on with their life, there's an increased risk for autoimmune disease and lymphoma. And
that's high yield. An increased risk for both autoimmune disease and lymphoma. Okay, the next
disorder is called IgA deficiency. And the idea here is that the patients have a low serum and
mucosal IgA. This is the most common immunoglobulin deficiency. And guess what kind of infections
they're going to get? Mucosal infections. IgA is on the surface of, is on mucosal surfaces and helps to
protect against mucosal infections, especially viral infections. And so these patients will get
an increased risk of mucosal infections, especially viral. Now, maybe we could stop here for a second.
I can tie in a little bit, do a little bit of circular review. Do you know which GI disease is
associated with IgA deficiency? Otherwise stated, in which GI disease is there a high propensity of
patients who have IgA deficiency? The answer is celiac disease. And that's something to be familiar with
clinically, as well as for examinations. So in celiac disease, one of the associations of celiac disease
is IgA deficiency. And we'll talk about that when we do the GI lectures as well. Okay, hyper-Igm syndrome.
I actually like this one. This shows up a lot on exams. It's a great way to test a little bit of normal
immunology. So what's the idea here? It's characterized by too much IgM. And the key feature
here is that the patients have a mutation in the CD40, something to do with CD40, CD40 ligand or CD40
receptor. So let's go back and review for a minute. Can we remind ourselves that there were two ways by
which B cells get activated? I'm going to wipe this out just to go back and do a little review.
There were two ways, as I talked about in the prior lecture, in which B cells can be activated.
The first way is for a naive B cell, which basically looks like this and expresses IgM on its surface,
correct? And I said that one way for this cell to get activated is that an antigen binds IgM
on the surface, and that that then results in an IgM-secreting plasma cell. And that plasma cell
can then produce IgM. So that's one way by which the B cell, sorry, by which, yeah, by which the B cell
can be activated. Okay? So bear that in the back of your mind. A second way, I'm going to go back and
give you another whiteboard here. A second way by which the B cell can be activated is that the B cell,
so let's pretend that this is the B cell, can actually internalize the antigen and present the
antigen instead on, let's say that this is MHC class II, right? So if the B cell presents the antigen
on MHC class II, the CD4 positive T cell will bind that antigen, and that will result in the first
stimulus. But remember that there's a second stimulus that occurs, and that is a CD40 stimulus,
and that's really what you have to remember. The CD40 will be, is basically expressed by the B cell,
and it binds CD40 receptor on the T cell, and it's the binding of CD40 to its receptor that provides the
second signal, so that the CD4 positive T cell can get activated, CD4 positive T cell, and when the
CD4 positive T cell gets activated, it's going to produce IL-4, remember the two key ones are IL-4
and IL-5, and IL-4 and IL-5 will basically go back and hit the B cell, allowing the B cell to mature
and to undergo class switching, so that eventually that B cell can produce IgA, IgG, and IgE.
Okay, with all of that background, now we go back to this disease, which is called hyper-IgM syndrome.
It's characterized by an elevated IgM. In this particular disease, the first mechanism of
activation of B cell is okay. It's intact. So that what can happen is antigen can bind the B cell,
and the B cell can produce IgM. However, the second way of activating B cell, which was dependent on CD40,
is mutated. Either CD40 is mutated or the CD40 receptor is mutated, but the problem is that that
second signal cannot be delivered to the helper T cell. If the second signal cannot be delivered to
the helper T cell during B cell activation, then those cytokines, i.e. IL-4 and IL-5, necessary for Ig class
switching cannot be produced. So IgA will be low, IgG will be low, and IgE will be low. But IgM will be
high. Why is IgM high? Because the very first mechanism of activating the B cells, where they
overproduced IgM, is intact. All right, so that's the way to remember this. Now what's going to happen?
Because IgA is low, you're going to get mucosal infections. Because IgG is low, you're going to
recurrent pus forming infections, because IgG is an opsonin. So these are some of the key features
and clinical features that would be present in this disorder. Very high yield, okay? Hyper IgM
syndrome. It's very high yield because it allows for examiners to go back and test you on some basic
principles of immunology. Okay, and then, and it really goes downhill from here. So Wiscott-Aldrich
syndrome, basically you just have to sort of memorize that this is characterized by a triad,
and that triad is thrombocytopenia. That's number one. So they get an increased risk of
bleeding. They can get petechia in the skin, for example. Petechia in the skin and mucosal
membrane bleeding. They get eczema, so they'll get a skin rash. And the patients get recurrent
infections, and they can get, they have defective both humoral and cellular immunity, so they
get a variety of infections, all right? So that's the Wiscott-Aldrich syndrome. This is due
a mutation in the Wiscott-Aldrich syndrome protein. No rocket science. Wiscott-Aldrich
syndrome protein, and that is X-linked, okay? Another group, another circumstance in which
we may find immunodeficiency is where there is complement deficiency. There's really two
high yields here. Number one, if a patient is deficient in anything from C5 to C9, so C5,
C6, C7, or C8, or C9, there'll be an increased risk of Neisseria infection, and that is high
yield, okay? That's one. And then two, if the patients have a deficiency in something called
C1 inhibitor, they will develop edema of skin and mucosal surfaces, and that's called hereditary
angioedema. Now what's the idea here? Remember that C1 is an important activator of complement,
and it's an important early protein in the complement pathway, and when it gets activated,
it turns on complement. Now in order to decrease the potential risk of activation of C1, we have
something called C1 inhibitor, which helps to sort of control C1 so that it doesn't get activated
except when necessary. But if the inhibitor is deficient, we're going to get over-activation of C1.
Over-activation of C1 will over-activate complement, and the consequence of over-activation of complement
will be vasodilation, increased vascular permeability, and some of the classic findings
of acute inflammation, particularly the formation of edema. And to these patients, the consequence
is something called hereditary angioedema. The classic finding is edema of the skin and mucosal
membranes, especially periorbital. That's classic. And so I threw in a little picture here. This is a little
picture in which we see that this child's eyes are edematous, or the skin surrounding the eyes
is edematous. And this is a classic image of hereditary angioedema. And that really closes off
this particular section of immunodeficiencies. And so we'll go ahead and stop there, give you a little
chance to catch up, and then we'll continue on with autoimmune disorders.
So